Robert Whitehead Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Robert Whitehead Papers 1947-2002 (bulk 1950-1996)
ML31.W53
Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002
approximately 22,500 items 75 containers 38.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Robert Whitehead was a Tony Award-winning theatrical producer and director. The collection contains production files, correspondence, business papers, writings, photographs, costume and set renderings, programs and promotional materials, scripts, and other materials related to his life and career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Atkinson, Brooks, 1894-1984--Correspondence.; Caldwell, Zoe--Correspondence.; Caldwell, Zoe.; Clurman, Harold, 1901-1980--Correspondence.; Inge, William--Correspondence.; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.; Plummer, Christopher--Correspondence.; Prince, Harold, 1928- --Correspondence.; Stevens, Roger L.; Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002--Archives.; Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002--Correspondence.; Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002--Photographs.; Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002.; Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002.
Organizations
Dramatists Guild.; Repertory Theater of Lincoln Center.
Subjects
Drama--20th century.; Performing arts--United States.; Theater--Production and direction--United States.; Theater--Study and teaching.; Theater--United States.; Theatrical companies--United States.; Theatrical producers and directors.
Form/Genre
Articles.; Awards.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographic prints.; Posters.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Renderings (Drawings).; Scripts (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Zoe Caldwell, 2003.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Sound and video recordings from the Robert Whitehead Papers have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. An inventory of this material is available in the Music Division's collection file.
Related Material
The
Leonard Bernstein Collection
in the Music Division has various materials relating to Whitehead. In addition, the Library of Congress Manuscript Division holds the following collections which contain materials relating to Whitehead:
Hume Cronyn and Jessica Tandy Papers (annual file)
(Hume Cronyn was Robert Whitehead’s cousin),
Lucy Kroll Papers (client file)
,
George Middleton Papers (business correspondence)
and the
Joshua Logan Papers (correspondence)
.
Access and Restrictions
The Robert Whitehead Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Robert Whitehead (1916-2002) was an American theatrical director and producer. Born March 3, 1916 in Montreal, Whitehead was the son of William Thomas Whitehead, an owner of textile mills, and Lena Mary Labatt Whitehead, an opera singer. He grew up in Montreal and attended college at Trinity College School in Port Hope, Ontario.
After graduation, Whitehead worked briefly as a commercial photographer before moving to New York City to pursue work in the theater. He studied acting at the New York School of Theatre and in 1936, made his New York debut in the play Night Must Fall. Whitehead then joined the Barter Theater in Abingdon, Virginia and assumed many roles, including acting, stage managing, and building sets.
From 1942 to 1945, Whitehead served in World War II as an ambulance driver in North Africa, Italy, and India. Upon his return from the war, he abandoned acting in favor of producing. His first production was Robinson Jeffers' Medea starring Australian actress Judith Anderson and Shakespearean actor John Gielgud. Its success earned Whitehead a reputation as someone who could produce financially successful works with artistic merit. He would later direct the 1982 revival of Medea starring his wife, Zoe Caldwell (whom he married in 1968) in the title role and Judith Anderson as the Nurse.
Whitehead's career as a producer spanned over 50 years. Among his most successful productions were The Member of the Wedding (1950), The Prime of Miss Jean Brodie (1968), A Matter of Gravity (1975), The West Side Waltz (1981), Lillian (1986), A Few Good Men (1989), and Master Class (1996). In 1960, Whitehead and Elia Kazan were asked to head the first Lincoln Center theater company. By 1964, the Lincoln Center Repertory Theater was established and opened its first season with After the Fall, written by Arthur Miller and starring Jason Robards. Kazan and Whitehead left the company that year amid controversies involving conflicts with the board of directors.
Whitehead had a longstanding relationship with Arthur Miller and produced many of his later plays. He won a Tony Award in 1984 for his restaging of Death of a Salesman starring Dustin Hoffman. Other playwrights with whom Whitehead worked closely included Tennessee Williams, Carson McCullers, Eugene O’Neill, Thornton Wilder, Friedrich Durrenmatt, Jean Anouilh, and Robert Bolt. Whitehead was often an integral part of the creative process as well, revising scripts, making casting decisions and promoting plays once they had opened.
Whitehead won six Tony Awards, including a 1996 best play honor for his production of Master Class starring Zoe Caldwell. In 2002, just weeks before his death, Whitehead received a Special Lifetime Achievement Tony Award celebrating his more than 60 years in the theater. He died of cancer at age 86 on June 15, 2002 at his home in Pound Ridge, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The Robert Whitehead Papers span the period 1947-2002, with the majority of materials dating from 1950-1996. They include production files, correspondence, business papers, published and unpublished writings, photographs, costume and set renderings, programs and promotional materials, scripts, and biographical materials.
The Production Files series chiefly consists of scripts and business papers related to plays Whitehead produced and directed. It also includes programs, photographs, correspondence with playwrights, actors, and investors, limited partnership agreements, and actor and production contracts. These files span the entire range of Whitehead's career as a producer from the 1940s through the 1990s. Notable files include scripts from his 1982 revival of Medea starring Judith Anderson and his wife Zoe Caldwell, scripts and correspondence from the 1968 production of The Prime of Miss Jean Brodie, and correspondence with Katharine Hepburn about the 1976 production of A Matter of Gravity and the 1981 production of The West Side Waltz. The "Dramatist Guild agreements" file, located within the Business Papers series, also contains contracts for many of Whitehead's signature productions. All files are arranged alphabetically by show title.
Correspondence in the collection includes business and personal letters sent and received by Whitehead, beginning with papers related to the 1947 production of Medea and ending with Whitehead's death. Notable correspondents include Brooks Atkinson, Harold Clurman, Bill Inge, Harold Prince, and Christopher Plummer. All files are arranged chronologically by year. The Business Papers series contains mostly letters and contracts related to theatrical education projects, theater companies with which Whitehead was associated, and awards or memorial projects. The majority of the materials are related to Whitehead's tenure as head of the Lincoln Center Repertory Theater. Of particular interest is correspondence regarding Whitehead's decision to resign from this organization and the ensuing controversy with its board of directors. All files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
The Writings series contains articles, speeches, and book materials written by and about Whitehead. Included are Whitehead's introductions to biographies of Arthur Miller and Harold Clurman, interviews about his career in the theater, materials from his 80th birthday tribute, and writings related to Whitehead's death and memorial. Reviews, articles, and fliers pertaining to Whitehead's productions are arranged by title in the Publicity Files series. Photographs in the collection are mostly images of Whitehead alone or with friends and family members. Interspersed are photos of friends and acquaintances, including Arthur Miller and business partner Roger Stevens. The remaining materials consist of piano-vocal scores or parts for Midgie Purvis and The Conquering Hero, scripts sent to Whitehead for his consideration that were never produced, memorabilia and writings related to Zoe Caldwell, awards, posters, and costume renderings from several of his productions.
Organization of the Robert Whitehead Papers
The Robert Whitehead Papers are organized in eight series:
Production Files, 1947-2001
Correspondence, 1947-2002
Business Papers, 1947-2000
Writings, 1950-2002
Publicity Files, 1958-1986
Photographs, 1961-1997
Music, 1961
Miscellany, 1949-2002
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012562126
Container List
- Production Files, 1947-2001 (Box 1-46, 73)
  Correspondence, business papers, scripts, photographs, programs, contracts, and other materials related to Whitehead's stage productions. Researchers should also examine the "Dramatist Guild agreements" file, located within the business papers series, for additional contracts pertaining to signature productions.
  Arranged alphabetically by title of production and by subject therein.
  - 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue (1976) (Box-folder 1-2/7)
  - After the fall (1964-1965) (Box-folder 2/8-9, 3/1)
  - The archbishop's ceiling (1977) (Box-folder 3/2-6)
  - Ardele (1975) (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Banderol (1962) (Box-folder 3/8)
  - The bedroom farce (1979) (Box-folder 3/9, 4, 5/1-2)
  - Bequest to the nation (1970) (Box-folder 5/3-6)
  - Betrayal (1979) (Box-folder 5/7-12, 6/1-2)
  - Broken glass (1994) (Box-folder 6/3-5)
  - Bus stop (1955-1956) (Box-folder 6/6-9)
  - But for whom, Charlie (1964, ANTA) (Box-folder 6/10, 7/1)
  - Carmelina (1979) (Box-folder 7/2-7)
  - The changeling (1964) (Box-folder 7/8)
  - The cold wind and the warm (1958-1959) (Box-folder 7/9-10, 8/1-4)
  - The confidential clerk (1954) (Box-folder 8/5-9)
  - The conquering hero (1961) (Box-folder 8/10-13, 9/1)
  - The creation of the world and other business (1972) see also Two-play venture (Box-folder 9/2-8, 10/1-2)
  - Crime and punishment (1947-1948), Clipping only (Box-folder 10/3)
  - The culper ring (undated) (Box-folder 10/4-5)
  - The day the money stopped (1958) (Box-folder 10/6-9, 11/1-3)
  - Death of a salesman (1984) (Box-folder 11/4-7, 12/1)
  - Deathtrap (undated) (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Desire under the elms (1952), Clipping only (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Economic necessity (circa 1974) (Box-folder 12/4)
  - The emperor's clothes (1953) (Box-folder 12/5-9)
  - The family man (1953) (Box-folder 12/10-11)
  - A few good men (1989-1991) (Box-folder 13/1-3)
  - Finishing touches (1973) see also Two-play venture (Box-folder 13/4-8, 14/1-5)
  - The flowering peach (1954-1955) (Box-folder 15/1-5)
  - Four saints in three acts (1952), Clipping only (Box-folder 15/6)
  - Foxy (1964) (Box-folder 15/7-8)
  - Golden boy (1952), Clipping only (Box-folder 15/9)
  - Goldilocks (1958-1959) (Box-folder 15/10-13, 16/1-6)
  - A hole in the head (1957) (Box-folder 16/7-13, 17/1)
  - Incident at Vichy (1964-1965), Clipping only (Box-folder 17/2-4)
  - The kidders (1950), Clipping only (Box-folder 17/5)
  - The last meeting of the Knights of the White Magnolia (1976) see also A Texas trilogy (Box-folder 17/6-7)
  - Lillian (1986) (Box-folder 17/8-12, 18/1-8)
  - Lu Ann Hampton Laverty Oberlander (1976) see also A Texas trilogy (Box-folder 18/9-10)
  - Lunch hour (1980-1981) (Box-folder 19/1-8, 20/1-7, 73/1)
  - A man for all seasons (1961-1963) (Box-folder 20/6-7, 21/2-10, 22/1-3)
  - Master class (1995-1997) (Box-folder 22/4-10)
  - A matter of gravity (1976) (Box-folder 23/1-8, 24/1-8, 25/1-6)
  - Medea (1982) (Box-folder 26/1-15, 27/1-5)
  - The member of the wedding (1950-1951) (Box-folder 27/6-12)
  - Midgie Purvis (1961) (Box-folder 27/13-14, 28/1)
  - Mrs. McThing (1952-1953) (Box-folder 28/2-5)
  - Much ado about nothing (1959) (Box-folder 28/6-7)
  - No man's land (1976) (Box-folder 28/8-15, 29/1)
  - Old times (1971-1972) (Box-folder 29/2-10)
  - The oldest living graduate (1976) see also A Texas trilogy (Box-folder 29/11-12)
  - Orpheus descending (1957) (Box-folder 30/1-4)
  - Park your car in Harvard Yard (1991-1992) (Box-folder 30/5-13)
  - The petition (1986) (Box-folder 31/1-10, 32/1-4, 73/2)
  - The physicists (1964), Clipping only (Box-folder 32/5)
  - The price (1968-1969) (Box-folder 32/6-12, 33/1-3, 73/3)
  - The prime of Miss Jean Brodie (1968) (Box-folder 33/4-11, 34/1-5)
  - The prince of Grand Street (1978) (Box-folder 34/6-10, 35/1-7, 73/4)
  - The prodigal daughter (1973) (Box-folder 35/8, 36/1-3)
  - The remarkable Mr. Pennypacker (1953-1954) (Box-folder 36/4-7)
  - Resurrection blues (2001) (Box-folder 36/8-9)
  - Saint Joan (1954) (Box-folder 36/10-13)
  - Semmelweiss (1977-1978) (Box-folder 37/1-7)
  - Separate tables (1956-1957) (Box-folder 38/1-6)
  - Sheep on the runway (1970) (Box-folder 38/7-11, 39/1-2)
  - The skin of our teeth (1955) (Box-folder 39/3-5)
  - The sorrows of Frederick (1970) (Box-folder 39/6-10, 40/1)
  - The speed of darkness (1991) (Box-folder 40/2-6)
  - Sunday breakfast (1952), Clipping only (Box-folder 40/7)
  - Tamburlaine the great (1956), Ledger book only (Box-folder 40/8)
  - Tartuffe (1965) (Box-folder 40/9)
  - A Texas trilogy (1976) see also The last meeting of the Knights of the White Magnolia; Lu Ann Hampton Laverty Oberlander; The oldest living graduate (Box-folder 40/10-11, 41/1-7, 42/1-4)
  - The time of the cuckoo (1952-1953) (Box-folder 42/5-9)
  - A touch of the poet (1958-1959) (Box-folder 42/10-12, 43/1-3)
  - Two-play venture (1972-1988) see also The creation of the world and other business and Finishing touches, Financial documents for The Creation of the World and Other Business and Finishing Touches (Box-folder 44/1)
  - Up from paradise (1974) (Box-folder 44/2)
  - A view from the bridge (1955), Clipping only (Box-folder 44/3)
  - The visit (1958) (Box-folder 44/4-10)
  - The waltz of the toreadors (1957) (Box-folder 45/1-4)
  - The West Side waltz (1981-1982) (Box-folder 45/5-8, 46/1-10)
  - Where's Daddy? (1966), Clipping only (Box-folder 46/11)
  - Unidentified, Costume renderings (Box-folder 73/5)
- Correspondence, 1947-2002 (Box 47-53)
  Miscellaneous business and personal letters sent and received by Whitehead.
  Arranged chronologically by year. Selected correspondence from notable personalities are arranged alphabetically by last name following the general correspondence.
  - 1947-1969 (Box-folder 47/1-23)
  - 1970-1979 (Box-folder 48/1-10)
  - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 49/1-5)
  - 1985-1989 (Box-folder 50/1-5)
  - 1990-1995 (Box-folder 51/1-6)
  - 1996-1999 (Box-folder 52/1-7)
  - 2000-2002 (Box-folder 53/1-3)
  - Undated (Box-folder 53/4)
  - Clurman, Harold, 1949-1970 (Box-folder 53/5)
  - Inge, William, 1961-1970 (Box-folder 53/6)
  - Plummer, Christopher, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 53/7)
  - Prince, Harold, 1999 (Box-folder 53/8)
- Business Papers, 1947-2000 (Box 54-59)
  Chiefly letters, financial documents, and contracts related to theatrical education projects or theater companies with which Whitehead was associated, especially Lincoln Center. The "Dramatist Guild agreements" file is of particular interest and contains contracts for many shows listed among the production files.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Agnes de Mille Foundation, 1997-1998 (Box 54/1)
  - Agnes de Mille memorial, 1994 (Box-folder 54/2)
  - American Conservatory Theatre, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 54/3)
  - American National Theatre and Academy, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 54/4)
  - American Shakespeare Festival, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 54/5)
  - American Theatre Wing, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 54/6)
  - Barter Theatre, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 54/7)
  - The Broadway Alliance, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 54/8)
  - The Century Association, 2000 (Box-folder 54/9)
  - Department of State - Ad hoc drama panel, 1959-1965 (Box-folder 55/1)
  - Dominion Consultant Associates, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 55/2)
  - Dramatist Guild agreements, 1953-1962, Includes contracts for Goldilocks (Box-folder 55/3-6)
  - Institute for Advanced Studies in the Theatre Arts, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 56/1)
  - Lincoln Center, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 56/2-12, 57/1-7)
  - National Council on the Arts / National Arts Foundation, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 57/8)
  - National Theatre, 1976, Contracts for No Man's Land (Box-folder 57/9)
  - National Theatre School of Canada, 1964 (Box-folder 57/10)
  - Neighborhood Playhouse School of Theatre, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 57/11)
  - Office of Cultural Affairs, 1963 (Box-folder 58/1)
  - Play reports, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 58/2)
  - Plays optioned but not produced, 1956-1957, 1963 (Box-folder 58/3)
  - The Producers' Theatre, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 58/4)
  - Seattle Repertory Theatre, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 58/5)
  - Stratford Shakespeare Festival, 1964 (Box-folder 58/6)
  - Theatre Development Fund, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 58/7-8)
  - Theatre Hall of Fame, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 58/9)
  - Trip to Russia, 1959 (Box-folder 58/10)
  - Whitehead-REA Productions, 1947, Stock certificates (Box-folder 58/11)
  - Whitehead-Stevens, 1969-1979, 1987, Includes correspondence from Roger Stevens, Alan Jay Lerner, and Burton Lane (Box-folder 58/13-14, 59/1-2)
- Writings, 1950-2002 (Box 60-61)
  Articles, speeches, and assorted draft materials.
  Organized in two subseries and arranged alphabetically by subject therein.
  - Writings by Whitehead, 1963-2000
    - Articles, 1963, 1994-2000 and undated (Box-folder 60/1)
    - The collected works of Harold Clurman, 1993, Forward (Box-folder 60/2)
    - Fund for New American Plays, 1994, Speech for award ceremony (Box-folder 60/3)
    - Interview, undated (Box-folder 60/4)
    - Psychology and Arthur Miller, 1969, Preface (Box-folder 60/5)
    - Speeches, 1969-1973, 1990 and undated (Box-folder 60/6)
  - Writings about Whitehead, 1950-2002
    - 80th birthday tribute, 1996 (Box-folder 61/1)
    - Articles, 1950-2002 (Box-folder 61/2-5)
    - Obituaries and memorial tributes, 2002 (Box-folder 61/6-7)
    - Production credits, 1995-1997 and undated (Box-folder 61/8)
- Publicity Files, 1958-1986 (Box 62-65)
  Reviews, miscellaneous clippings, fliers, and other promotional materials related to Whitehead's productions.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - The bedroom farce (1979) (Box-folder 62/1)
  - Betrayal (1979) (Box-folder 62/2-3)
  - The creation of the world and other business (1972) (Box-folder 62/4)
  - Death of a salesman (1984) (Box-folder 62/5-6)
  - Finishing touches (1973) (Box-folder 63/1)
  - Goldilocks (1958-1959) (Box-folder 63/2)
  - Lillian (1986) (Box-folder 63/3-4)
  - A man for all seasons (1961-1963) (Box-folder 63/5)
  - A matter of gravity (1976) (Box-folder 63/6)
  - Medea (1982) (Box-folder 64/1-3)
  - No man's land (1976) (Box-folder 64/4-5)
  - Old times (1971-1972) (Box-folder 65/1-2)
  - The price (1968-1969) (Box-folder 65/3)
  - Sheep on the runway (1970) (Box-folder 65/4)
- Photographs, 1961-1997 (Box 66, 73)
  Studio portraits, photographs from award ceremonies, and other miscellaneous images. Includes several photographs of Arthur Miller, Roger Stevens, and Zoe Caldwell.
  Arranged hierarchically by subject.
  - R. Whitehead, alone, 1983-1985 and undated (Box-folder 66/1)
  - R. Whitehead, with family, 1968 and undated (Box-folder 66/2)
  - R. Whitehead, with other people, 1961-1963, 1987, 1997 and undated, Includes: Arthur Miller, Roger Stevens (Box-folder 66/3, 73/6)
  - Other people, 1979-1983 and undated (Box-folder 66/4, 73/7)
  - Tony Awards, 1993-1995, Includes: Arthur Miller, Robert Dowling (Box-folder 66/5)
  - Unidentified productions, undated (Box-folder 66/6)
- Music, 1961 (Box 67-68)
  Piano-vocal scores or parts for The Conquering Hero and Midgie Purvis.
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Part sets are organized by instrument.
  - The conquering hero (1961), Piano-vocal scores (Box-folder 67/1-5, 68/1)
  - Midgie Purvis (1961), Parts (piano, drums, strings) (Box-folder 68/2-7)
- Miscellany, 1949-2002 (Box 69-72, 74-75)
  Awards, miscellaneous scripts and programs, posters, and other personal effects. Includes a variety of materials related to Zoe Caldwell's performing career.
  - Awards, 1969-1979, 1988-2002 (Box-folder 69/1-4)
  - Books, 1968-1996, Inscribed materials; Includes: Horton Foote; Barrie Stavis (Box 75)
  - Miscellaneous programs, 1949-1950, 1970 and undated (Box-folder 69/5)
  - Miscellaneous scripts, 1950, 1960-1975, 1993 and undated
    - Absurd person singular (A. Ayckbourn) (Box-folder 69/6)
    - The amazing flight of the gooney bird (D. Previn) (Box-folder 69/7-8)
    - Bus Riley (W. Inge) (Box-folder 69/9)
    - Caesarean operations (W. Inge) (Box-folder 69/10)
    - Colette (E. Jones) (Box-folder 70/1)
    - Don't go gentle (W. Inge) (Box-folder 70/2)
    - An enemy of the people (A. Miller) (Box-folder 70/3)
    - Fame (A. Miller) (Box-folder 70/4)
    - Free and clear (R. Anderson) (Box-folder 70/5)
    - The marriage of Mr. Mississippi (F. Dürrenmatt) (Box-folder 70/6)
    - Midwives turn manic (W. Inge) (Box-folder 70/7)
    - Natural affection (W. Inge) (Box-folder 70/8)
    - Overnight (W. Inge) (Box-folder 70/9)
    - A place on the Magdalena Flats (P. Jones) (Box-folder 70/10, 71/1-5)
    - The plains of St. Augustine (P. Jones) (Box-folder 71/6)
    - Voices (S. Griffin) (Box-folder 71/7)
    - The wicked pigeon ladies in the garden (M. Chase) (Box-folder 71/8)
  - Posters, 1968-1996, Includes: The bedroom farce; Master class; Lillian; The prime of Miss Jean Brodie (Box-folder 74/1-3)
  - Robert Whitehead Award, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 71/9)
  - Zoe Caldwell materials, 1976-2002 and undated, Correspondence, programs, publicity materials, and one speech (Box-folder 72/1-7)